<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse of the excellency of the soul, and the care every Christian ought to have of it in a sermon preach'd in Spanish / by Dr. Joseph de Barzia &amp; Zambrana ...</title>
            <title>De nobleza de el alma. English</title>
            <author>Barcia y Zambrana, José de.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26730</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1011</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10157</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11990384</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11990384</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52010</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26730)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52010)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 856:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse of the excellency of the soul, and the care every Christian ought to have of it in a sermon preach'd in Spanish / by Dr. Joseph de Barzia &amp; Zambrana ...</title>
                  <title>De nobleza de el alma. English</title>
                  <author>Barcia y Zambrana, José de.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Matthew Turner ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>On t.p.: Translated out of Spanish.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Apocrypha. --  Ecclesiasticus.</term>
               <term>Soul --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, Spanish --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52010:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE OF THE EXCELLENCY OF THE SOUL, AND THE Care every Chriſtian ought to have of it.</p>
            <p>IN A SERMON Preach'd in <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> By Dr. <hi>Joſeph de Barzia &amp; Zambrana,</hi> Canon and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Scripture in <hi>Granada.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of <hi>Spaniſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Matthew Turner,</hi> near <hi>Turn-Stile</hi> in <hi>Holborn.</hi> M DC LXXXV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="note">
            <pb facs="tcp:52010:2"/>
            <p>Note, that the Quotations of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are taken out of the Vulgar Edition.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52010:2"/>
            <head>A Diſcourſe <hi>of the Excellency of the</hi> Soul, <hi>and the Care every</hi> Chriſtian <hi>ought to have of it.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Eccleſiaſticus, <hi>cap.</hi> 10. <hi>ver.</hi> 31.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>Fili, in manſuetudine ſerva Animam tuam, &amp; da illi honorem ſecundum meritum ſuum.</p>
                  <p>Son, in mildneſs keep thy Soul, and give him honour according to his deſert.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IT is no ſmall Miſery and Confuſion, that through our own Fault, we know not our ſelves. We ſee Men daily employ'd in finding out the Courſe of the Stars, in diſcovering the Nature of Plants, the Temper of humane Bodies, and the Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of all other living Creatures; and this without the leaſt care of underſtanding the Soul, which gives them Life. Ah, what Induſtry (complains the great St. <hi>Baſil</hi>) <note place="margin">Baſ. ho. 10. in exam.</note> in making Anatomies, in taking the Body in pieces, to look into its moſt ſubtle and retired parts, and leave no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it undiſcern'd; while there's almoſt no Diligence in enquiring after the Souls Perfections; but ſo univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal a neglect of this kind, that Men ſeem to live, as if they had nothing more than Body; ſince to this alone are directed all their Endeavours, their Labours, and their Studies. This was the Caſe of the rich Man in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, <note place="margin">Lu. 12.</note> who ſpeaking to his Soul, ſaid, <hi>Requieſce, comede,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:52010:3"/> bibe, &amp; epulare, Take thy eaſe, eat, drink and be merry, thou haſt Goods laid up for many Years;</hi> whoſe Folly was ſo great, as St. <hi>Baſil</hi> takes notice, that he lived wholly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindful of the Excellency of his Soul, and was ſo alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether delivered up to the Appetites of his Fleſh, that thoſe groſs Proviſions, which he had hoarded up for his Body, he deſign'd ſhould ſerve for his Soul too. <hi>Tam improvidus es erga bona Animae, ut eſcas corporeas Animae</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Baſ. in Cat. D. Tho. Luc. 12</note> 
               <hi>tribuas.</hi> And, what is the greateſt Miſery, this blind In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderateneſs, we find every where, even amongſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, who, tho' they have received from the liberal hand of their Maker, a Soul ſo perfect; yet they apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves not at all to underſtand this Honour, but are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to live like Beaſts; which was lamented long ago by the Royal Prophet; <hi>Homo cum in honore eſſet, non</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 49.</note> 
               <hi>intellexit; comparatus eſt jumentis inſipentibus &amp; ſimilis factus eſt illis.</hi> And what other Reaſon, that men thus baſely degenerate, and become like Brutes; but only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they neglect the knowledge of their Souls? Of this we are inform'd from the Words of Chriſt, threatning the Soul, which is the Spouſe. She enquir'd of him in the Canticles, Where was the place of his Repoſe? <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi cubes in meridie?</hi> And he return'd her this Anſwer. <hi>Si ignoras te, O pulcherrima inter Mulieres, egredere, &amp; abi poſt veſtigia gregum. If thou know'ſt not thy ſelf, thou fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt among Women,</hi> that is (as <hi>Origen</hi> has it) if thou know'ſt not, O Soul, thy own great Beauty, thy own Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy above all corporeal Beings, if thou knoweſt not, that I made thee for the enjoyment of my ſelf: <hi>Egredere &amp; abi, Go forth and follow after the Steps of the Flocks;</hi> Go forth and live like the Beaſts, for thou deſerveſt not bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Company, if thou haſt no eſteem for thy own Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. <hi>Niſi cognoveris te ipſam, quae ſis, jubeo te exire, &amp; in ultimis gregum veſtigiis collocari.</hi> O formidable Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence! <note place="margin">Orig. expoſ. 2. Can. ho. 2.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:52010:3"/>
            <p>Give Ear, O Chriſtian: If thou know'ſt not thy ſelf, the holy Ghoſt ſays to thee; <hi>Egredere,</hi> Go out of my Houſe, that is, be gone from my Protection and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for they are no part of my care who underſtand not themſelves. <hi>Egredere,</hi> depart from my Fold; for he cannot be in my Flock, who is ignorant of himſelf. <hi>Egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere,</hi> be gone from my Friendſhip; for I have no Pleaſure in any, but ſuch as know what they are, and what they poſſeſs. <hi>Egredere,</hi> be gone even from thy ſelf too; for thou canſt have no comfort in thy own Being, if thou know'ſt not what thou art: <hi>Egredere,</hi> Go forth. But this is not all, whither muſt a Soul go, that is a Stranger to it ſelf? <hi>Abi poſt veſtigia gregum, Go follow after the Steps</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ber. ſer. 35. in Cant.</note> 
               <hi>of the Flocks,</hi> Go behind the Beaſts, ſince like them thou liveſt without Knowledge. And here, 'tis the remark of St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> 'tis not ſaid, <hi>Go forth,</hi> keep Company <hi>with</hi> the Beaſts; but <hi>follow after,</hi> go behind them; which is yet to be more miſerable than they: for theſe, with this Life end all their Miſeries: But that Soul, which has liv'd in a ſtupid ignorance of the Greatneſs and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of its own Being, with Death is to expect yet greater Miſeries, in Puniſhment of its Neglect. <hi>Abi poſt veſtigia gregum.</hi> So many Evils, and yet more, attend this one; whence we may ſee how much it ought to be the concern of every one to know themſelves.</p>
            <p>Upon this Conſideration it was, that St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> cry'd out; <hi>What Profits it a Man to know the whole World, if he know not himſelf?</hi> And in another Place, addreſſing himſelf to Man, he ſays; What is it you admire, in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the Grandeur and Beauty of the Sun and Stars, and the vaſt abyſſe of the Ocean? What is it you admire? <hi>Animi tui abyſſum intra.</hi> Call but your Thoughts in upon your ſelf, and ponder the Greatneſs and Excellency of <note place="margin">Aug. l. 4. de Trin.</note> thy Soul; and thou wilt be ſoon convinc'd, that none of theſe things are worth thy Admiration. The like Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52010:4"/> gave St. <hi>Bernard</hi> to his <hi>Eugenius: A te tua Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio incohet, Let thy Conſideration begin firſt with thy ſelf.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ber. l. 2. de Conſid.</note> Behold and underſtand what thou art; without this, all other Knowledge is but vain: <hi>Ne fruſtra extendaris ad alia, te neglecto.</hi> And for this reaſon, the four living Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſaw, (the Symbol of Holy Men, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to St. <hi>Gregory</hi>) being moved by the force of the Spirit, <hi>Went every one before his Face; Coram Facie ſuâ ambulabat:</hi> that is, they were preſent to themſelves. It being proper to thoſe who deſign towards Heaven, to <note place="margin">Ezek. c. 1. Ed. Vulg.</note> make the Knowledge of themſelves a great part of their Concern: and this not only as to the Miſery of the Body, but alſo as to the Excellency of the Soul; according to the Advice of St. <hi>Francis Sales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, ſince 'tis my whole Deſign in theſe Sermons, to excite all Faithful Chriſtians, to forſake the ways of Sin, and to ſpend their whole Endeavours in the gaining eternal Life; I'll lay before you to day, the great Beauty and Perfection of your Soul; that having conſidered this thoroughly, ye may underſtand how baſe and unworthy a thing it is, to blemiſh and defile it with Sin; and how much reaſon you have to conceive high Thoughts of it, proportion'd to its Excellency. This Method I borrow from the <hi>Canticles;</hi> where the Holy Ghoſt ſpeaking to his Beloved, the Soul, in the beginning ſays thus to her; <note place="margin">Cant. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Ecce tu pulcra es, amica mea, ecce tu pulcra es. Behold thou art fair, my Love,</hi> and then repeats it again, <hi>Behold thou art fair.</hi> And <hi>Origen</hi> gives the Reaſon, Becauſe the firſt thing he recommends to her is, <hi>to underſtand her ſelf;</hi> that ſo being ſenſible of her own Perfection, ſhe may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain ſuch noble Thoughts of her ſelf, as never to yield and ſubmit to Sin: <hi>Primo ſermone invitaevit Sponſus Spon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam, ut agnoſceret ſeipſam.</hi> Come therefore, Chriſtians, <note place="margin">Orig. ho. 3. in Cant.</note> raiſe your Thoughts, for a while, above all vain and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene Objects, that ſo your Minds may be wholly taken
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52010:4"/> up in the Contemplation of that Greatneſs, which you poſſeſs within ye. And I hope that this Conſideration will be a means, that ye conceive a horror againſt all Sin, and deteſt it; eſpecially if the Holy Ghoſt aſſiſts me with his divine Grace, and enables me to do this as I ought.</p>
            <q>Fili, in Manſuetudine ſerva animam tuam, &amp; da illi ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norem ſecundum meritum ſuum.</q>
            <q>Son, in Mildneſs keep thy Soul, and give him Honour ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Deſert. <hi>Eccl. c. 10. v. 31.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Before I propoſe to you the great worth of the Soul, <note place="margin">What the Soul is.</note> and how unreaſonable it is to debaſe it with Sin, I muſt ask one Queſtion: Chriſtians, do you know that you have rational Souls? 'Tis true, the external Shape and Figure you bear, ſpeak you to be Men; yet this falls ſhort of concluding you to be ſo. There were great Numbers in the Beginning of the World, which carried this Argument in their Face, and yet amongſt thoſe vaſt Multitudes there was only <hi>one,</hi> whom the Holy Ghoſt ſtiles <hi>Man;</hi> to wit, <hi>Enos,</hi> whoſe whole Employ was in the Service of God. <hi>Enos,</hi> ſays Euſebius Caeſarienſis, <note place="margin">L. 7. Praep. Eu. c. 3.</note> 
               <hi>verus homo interpretatur: neminem enim putant eſſe verum hominem, praeter eum, qui verum Deum agnoſcit &amp; piè co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit.</hi> This it is alone, which makes a Man worthy of that <hi>Name.</hi> Wherefore, ſays St. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> ſpeaking to Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, if with theſe external Lineaments of <hi>Men,</hi> I ſee the Actions and Cuſtoms of <hi>Beaſts,</hi> how can I reckon you amongſt the Number of Men? <hi>Qua ratione in hominum</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ho. 23. in Gen.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e poſſum numerum collocare?</hi> Tell me therefore, Sinner, <hi>haſt thou the Soul of a man?</hi> But I fear, thou haſt not yet conſider'd, whether thou haſt a Soul or no: 'tis the Miſery of too many Sinners, and that which a Holy Perſon ſadly deplor'd: <hi>Would it not be groſs</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Manſ. 1. c. 1.</note>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:52010:5"/> 
               <hi>Ignorance for one, being asked, Who he was, not to know himſelf, nor underſtand who was his Father or Mother, or what Country he was born in? If this then would be ſtrange Brutiſhneſs, incomparably greater is that which is found in us, when we endeavour not to know what we are, but fix our Thoughts upon theſe Bodies, and know not that we have Souls, but only in groſs, in as much as we have heard it, and becauſe Faith tells us ſo; but what Good this Soul com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes, who lives within it, or its great Value, we ſeldom conſider; and ſo take but little Care to preſerve its Beauty, being wholly intent in poliſhing the Roughneſs of this Caſe, and looking after the Walls of this Caſtle, which are theſe Bodies.</hi> Thus this devout Lady lamented the miſerable Neglect of Men in not endeavouring to underſtand the Excellency of their Souls.</p>
            <p>But let this Neglect, Chriſtians, at length have an end: You have all Souls; and ſuch as have any doubt in this Point, St. <hi>Chryſostom</hi> invites to the Sight of a Corps: Behold, ſays he, how foul it is, how loathſome and full <note place="margin">Hom. 12. in Gen.</note> of Horror, and without Motion; and this, becauſe 'tis left by that Soul, which gave it Life. Let any one move his Hand, is it not the Soul that gives the motion? You have a vegetative Life, as in Trees; you have a ſenſitive, as in Animals; and whence this, but from the Soul? But more than this, you ſee that you remember things that are paſt, you underſtand things, and frame Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes upon them, you make Inferences, deducing one thing from another. You have a Propenſion to Good, an Averſion to Evil; why all this is from the Soul. In fine, the Soul is a rational, intellectual, and ſpiritual Subſtance, created by God of nothing. 'Tis a Spirit, like to the Angels, immortal and eternal; it had a Beginning, but ſhall never have an end: 'tis whole in the whole Body, and whole in every part. And what is moſt admirable, 'tis ſo capacious, that it can be ſatisfied and fill'd by none
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52010:5"/> but God that made it. 'Tis dignified moreover with a <hi>free Will,</hi> by which it has the <hi>Liberty</hi> of embracing either Vice or Vertue, and ſo becomes worthy of Puniſhment or a Reward; which was the thing intimated by God to <hi>Cain: Nonne ſi bene egeris, recipies? Si autem malè, ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim in foribus peccatum tuum aderit.</hi> This is, Chriſtian, <note place="margin">Gen. 4.</note> that Queen which reſides in that mean Palace of thy Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: 'tis a Pearl enclos'd in that rough Shell; 'tis the Lady and Miſtreſs of that Houſe; 'tis the Epitome of all created Perfections. O bleſſed for ever be the Goodneſs of our Creator, for the Excellency of this Work. But ſtay here a little, Chriſtians, and ponder ſeriouſly, what it is that God has put into your own hands: <hi>in manu conſilii tui; viz.</hi> the choice of <hi>Good</hi> or <hi>Evil,</hi> of Vertue or Vice, and that to work out your Salvation, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, is left in ſome manner to the Determination of your own <hi>Free Will.</hi> See this a little.</p>
            <p>In the Creation of the World, the Works of God had no ſooner receiv'd their Being from his omnipotent Hand, but they alſo receiv'd their Approbation of being <hi>good.</hi> He made the <hi>Light,</hi> and <hi>God ſaw the Light, that it was good. Vidit Deus lucem, quod eſſet bona.</hi> The ſame is repeated five times, at the Birth of other Creatures; But when <hi>Man</hi> comes to be made, we don't read that God ſhould ſay, that <hi>he was good.</hi> And what can be the Reaſon of this? Is Man leſs deſerving than the other Works of the Creation? Shall they be welcom'd into the World with a <hi>Bleſſing,</hi> and is there none for <hi>Man,</hi> who contains the Perfections of them all? Are the Beaſts, the Birds, the Fiſhes, more priviledg'd than <hi>Man,</hi> who is their Lord and Sovereign? No, ſays St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> they are not. And the reaſon why they, at their coming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the World, meet with an Approbation of being <hi>good,</hi> and not <hi>man,</hi> is, Becauſe at their firſt ſtep into a <hi>Being,</hi> they are perfect, and compleat as to their Subſtance, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52010:6"/> any dependance of any <hi>free Operation</hi> or <hi>Choice,</hi> of which they are incapable. But <hi>Man,</hi> though he comes like them, <hi>thus</hi> compleat into the World, yet he cannot be ſaid to be <hi>perfect;</hi> becauſe his Perfection and laſt Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment has a Dependance on his own <hi>free Will.</hi> For, if he <hi>will,</hi> by the Grace of God, he may be <hi>good;</hi> and if he <hi>will,</hi> through his own <hi>Malice,</hi> he may become <hi>evil.</hi> So that though at the firſt Inſtant of his Creation, he was equally the Work of God with other Creatures, yet having not exercis'd his <hi>Liberty</hi> in the <hi>choice</hi> of <hi>Good,</hi> his Approbation is ſuſpended, till it appears to which ſide he apply himſelf, making choice either of Good or Evil. <hi>Ideo homo non ante laudatur,</hi> ſays St. <hi>Ambroſe, quia non in forenſi pelle, ſed in interiore homine antè probandus,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Amb. de Inſt. Virg. c. 2.</note> 
               <hi>ſic praedicandus eſt.</hi> But let me clear this Point a little far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the ancient <hi>Romans,</hi> 'twas a Cuſtom, when they ſent forth Souldiers to the War, to deliver to every <note place="margin">Pier. l. 42.</note> one a <hi>white</hi> Buckler; that hence they might underſtand, that if at their Return they expected Rewards of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, they ſhould ſo behave themſelves in the War, that with the deſcription of their own Geſts and Atchievements, they might fill up the <hi>White</hi> of their <hi>Shields.</hi> And for this Reaſon, ſays <hi>Rabbanus,</hi> they were call'd in Latine, <hi>Scuta; Scutum dictum, quaſi Sculptum, quod in ipſo, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiqui</hi> 
               <note place="margin">L. 20. de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niv. c. 12.</note> 
               <hi>ſua facta ſignabant.</hi> The <hi>Roman</hi> Souldier therefore, muſt take care how he behaves himſelf in the War, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to expect no greater Honour at his Return, than he gains by his own Proweſs and Valour; he carries forth with him a <hi>white</hi> Shield, to be blazon'd with his own Actions. See now Chriſtians, the Soul of Man is call'd by the Philoſopher, a <hi>ſmooth</hi> and <hi>plain Table,</hi> which has nothing painted or decipher'd on it. When God puts it into this World, he ſends it to the <hi>War. Militia eſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta hominis ſuper terram. The Life of Man upon Earth is a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Job c, 7. Ed. Vulg.</note>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:52010:6"/> 
               <hi>Warfare:</hi> it carries with it a <hi>Free Will,</hi> which is, as it were, a <hi>white Buckler;</hi> that ſo, by a true Chriſtian Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, having won many Victories over Vice and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, they may be all engraven and diſplayed on it; thus to gain Honour and Perfection, and at the hour of Death to receive the Commendation of him, who at its Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſent it forth to Battel.</p>
            <p>Look back now, Faithful, and ſee how long 'tis ſince you came into this World; for ſo long 'tis ſince you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd the Campagne with your <hi>white Shields.</hi> What is it that you have engraven on them? How have you em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd your <hi>free Will?</hi> Have you made War againſt Vice, or Vertue? Have you follow'd the Colours of Satan, or the Standard of Jeſus Chriſt? In what Condition are your Souls? Are they defil'd with the Abominations of Sin? O baſe and unworthy Choice! How can you ever expect the Welcome and Approbation of your Maker? 'Tis a thing <hi>St. Auguſtin</hi> could never ceaſe to admire, That Man <note place="margin">Ser. 12. de Ver. Dom. in Mat.</note> ſhould deſire every thing that is for his ſervice, to be <hi>good</hi> about him, except his <hi>Soul.</hi> You deſire, ſays the <hi>Saint,</hi> that the Fields ſhould be <hi>good,</hi> in which you ſow; that the Timber ſhould be <hi>good,</hi> which you purchaſe; that the Houſe ſhould be <hi>good,</hi> in which you live; that the Horſe ſhould be <hi>good,</hi> which you buy; and that the Cloaths ſhould be <hi>good</hi> which you wear: <hi>ſolam Animam vis habere malam; Only your Soul, you don't care how ill it is. Quid te offendiſti?</hi> complains the ſame holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Quid de te, tu ipſe meruiſti?</hi> What Injury has thy Soul done thee? What is the Reaſon, thou haſt deſerved ſo ill of thy ſelf? That being induſtrious to provide eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing that's good, thou haſt Patience to ſee only one thing ill about thee, and that's thy <hi>Soul? Praepone vitam tuam caligae tuae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that thou may'ſt ſee, that thy Soul deſerves not this Neglect from thy Hands, the Holy Ghoſt ſays to you
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52010:7"/> to day, <hi>Da illi honorem ſecundum meritum ſuum; Give it Honour according to its deſert.</hi> And this it is that I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend you ſhould conſider now, in what Eſteem you ought to have your Soul; how much it deſerves, being compar'd to the <hi>Body;</hi> how much it deſerves, for being the Image of God: what Reſpect is due to it, for being redeem'd by the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt; and finally, what Care you ought to have of it, for that it is created for the Fruition of eternal Glory. <hi>Da illi honorem ſecundum meritum ſuum; Give it Honour according to its Deſert.</hi> I begin now.</p>
            <p>One of the principal Duties of a Chriſtian, is, to eſteem <note place="margin">The Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Soul compar'd to the Body.</note> all things according to their Worth and Dignity, giving to them the Place that is due to them, either as to <hi>Love,</hi> or <hi>Hatred.</hi> And this the Holy Spouſe, in the <hi>Canticles,</hi> reckons for one of the chief <hi>Preſents</hi> ſhe had receiv'd from the Divine Spirit; to wit, <hi>That he had plac'd in order her Love and Affections; Ordinavit in me Charitatem.</hi> So <note place="margin">Cant. 2.</note> that whoſoever bears a Love to that which he ought to hate, or gives the <hi>firſt</hi> Place in his Affections to what ſhould only have the <hi>laſt,</hi> does not only not do like a Chriſtian, but even not like a rational Creature. When <hi>Aeneas</hi> fled from his Country, now going into Aſhes, his Enemies gave him leave to take with him out of that common Ruine, the thing which was moſt <hi>dear</hi> unto him: and he immediately made choice of <hi>his Gods.</hi> And this his Zeal was ſo well liked by the <hi>Grecians,</hi> that upon this, 'twas permitted him to <hi>ſave</hi> ſomething elſe: then he took his Father. A third time Liberty was given him, and he nam'd his Relations and Friends; preferring theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Goods and Riches. At which Order in his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, they were ſo well ſatisfied, that he had forthwith leave to redeem every thing that belong'd to him, from thoſe Flames. Now ſee Chriſtian, God created the <hi>Soul,</hi> he form'd the <hi>Body,</hi> and gave a Being to all other things,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52010:7"/> for the Service of <hi>Man;</hi> but ſo, that all was to be <hi>ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate</hi> to the Soul. Now the buſineſs of a Chriſtian is, to ſee that the <hi>Soul</hi> has the Precedency in all Occaſions, and that he has always a greater Eſteem for it, than for the <hi>Body,</hi> or any other tranſient and ſublunary thing: ſo that whenſoever any danger threatens, his firſt care ought to be, to <hi>ſecure</hi> his <hi>Soul,</hi> altho' all the reſt periſh. Let Life, let Honour, let Poſſeſſions, let Friends and all go, rather than for the ſaving of theſe, to hazard the loſs of his Soul. For, <hi>What can it profit a man,</hi> according to our B. Redeemer's Words, <hi>to gain the whole World, if he loſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26.</note> 
               <hi>his Soul? Quid prodeſt homini?</hi> Suppoſing therefore this <hi>Order</hi> according to the Worth of things, let us proceed, and ſee what Compariſon there can be betwixt the <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Body,</hi> as to the Eſteem, that is due to them. And for the ſetting forth of this, I'll ask this one Queſtion:</p>
            <p>Seeing that the Soul of Man, according to the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> is a <hi>Spirit</hi> like to the Angels, what can be the Reaſon, that God ſhould confine and ſhut up this ſo noble a Creature, within the Limits of a Body, ſo infirm, and ſubject to ſo many Miſeries? If ſhe had been exempt from this clog of Earth, and liv'd alone, as the Angels do, ſhe had been freed from the Treachery of her Companion, the <hi>Fleſh.</hi> But no, ſays the <hi>great Nazianzen,</hi> this was not <note place="margin">Orat. 2. post Paſc.</note> agreeable to the <hi>Divine Providence; Ne ſicut Angelus, homo ſuperbiret, &amp; periret.</hi> God made choice, ſays he, of this means, ſo to ſecure her againſt the Temptation of her own Excellency. He created the Angels noble and glorious Spirits; but <hi>Lucifer,</hi> with the third part of that celeſtial Hoſt, viewing their own Excellency and Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſoon fell into Pride, and ſo from Heaven. God therefore, to prevent the loſs of the <hi>Soul,</hi> enclos'd it within a <hi>Caſe</hi> of Earth, thus to remove all Occaſions; and that Pride, as in the Angels, might not be her Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine. <hi>Ne ſicut Angelus, homo ſuperbiret &amp; periret.</hi> Such
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52010:8"/> therefore, O Chriſtian, is the <hi>Greatneſs</hi> of thy <hi>Soul,</hi> that God thought fit to caſt over it, a groſs and heavy <hi>Body,</hi> that ſo it might be out of danger of loſing it ſelf, in the Contemplation of its own <hi>Beauty</hi> and <hi>Perfection.</hi> This is the <hi>Poiſe</hi> which, <hi>Job</hi> ſays, God made to the Winds, <note place="margin">c. 28.</note> to wit, the <hi>Souls</hi> of Men, as St. <hi>Gregory</hi> expounds it; <note place="margin">L. 19. mor. c. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Qui fecit ventis pondus.</hi> That as the little <hi>Bee,</hi> graſping a Peeble, ſecures it ſelf from the Violence of a ſtormy Air; ſo the <hi>Soul,</hi> being check'd and kept down by a weight of <hi>Clay,</hi> may remain ſteddy and fix'd, and fruſtrate all the Attempts of <hi>Pride,</hi> endeavouring to raiſe her above her ſelf; ſo much care has the <hi>Soul</hi> coſt her Creator, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding means for her ſecurity. And according to this Doctrine now, <hi>What is the Body?</hi> But only the <hi>Caſe</hi> of this <hi>Jewel,</hi> the Slave of this Empreſs, the Ballaſt of this Ship. This is the <hi>Order</hi> they hold from the Appointment of God. But <hi>how</hi> are they rank'd by the Inordinacy of thy Malice? The Soul is the Lady and Empreſs; <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namini,</hi> ſaid God to <hi>Adam. Subter te erit Appetitus tuus,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 1.</note> he ſaid to <hi>Cain.</hi> Conſequently <hi>ſhe</hi> ought to be honour'd <note place="margin">Gen. 4.</note> and ſerv'd by the Body: <hi>Da illi honorem cui honor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petit;</hi> Give that Deference to the Soul which is due to it, as being the <hi>Chief. Honor animae debitus eſt,</hi> (writes <hi>C. A. lapide) ut illa quaſi Regina imperet Corpori, &amp; ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">10 Eccl.</note> 
               <hi>quaſi ſubditis &amp; ancillis.</hi> The <hi>Body,</hi> with all its Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ought to attend on, and ſerve the Soul, for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining Life everlaſting. How unreaſonable therefore is it, that the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> deſign'd for nothing, but to be a <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant</hi> and <hi>Slave,</hi> ſhould be careſs'd and waited on; and the <hi>Soul,</hi> a Queen and Monarch, ſhould be made to drudge? What a monſtrous kind of <hi>Diſorder</hi> is this, ſays St. <hi>Bernard?</hi> Could any Chriſtian, with Patience, ſee <note place="margin">L. Med. c. 3.</note> this in his Houſe? Why then does he ſuffer and allow of that within himſelf, which in his Family, 'tis not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble he ſhould endure? <hi>There are three things,</hi> ſays Solomon, <note place="margin">Prov. 30.</note>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:52010:8"/> 
               <hi>which diſturb the Earth, and the fourth it cannot ſuſtain. Per tria movetur terra, &amp; quartum non poteſt ſuſtinere.</hi> The firſt is, when a Servant reigns; the ſecond, a Fool that is fill'd with Meat; the third, an odious Woman, that is taken in Marriage: theſe are the three things by which the Earth is mov'd. But what is that which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable, and cannot be ſuſtain'd? <hi>Per ancillam, cum fuerit haeres Dominae ſuae;</hi> which the Septuagint read thus; <hi>Serva, cum Dominam ſuam ejecerit.</hi> 'Tis a Servant that commands and domineers over her Lady, and turns her out of doors. And hear now St. <hi>Antony</hi> of <hi>Padua</hi> expounding what this is; 'Tis the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> ſays he, when 'tis rais'd up, and takes the Command in hand, is in all things obſerv'd, obey'd, and waited on; while the <hi>Soul,</hi> being dethron'd, is neglected, ſcorn'd, deſpis'd, and made a <hi>Servant</hi> to her <hi>Slave:</hi> this it is that is intolerable. <hi>Domina eſt Ratio, ancilla eſt ſenſualitas, quam etiam terra ſuſtinere non poteſt, cum ſibi ipſi dominationem uſurpaverit</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ser. Dom. 9. Pent.</note> 
               <hi>Rationis.</hi> But I'll come now to Particulars.</p>
            <p>Come hither therefore, firſt, you <hi>Covetous</hi> Men; you, <note place="margin">The Sinner makes his Soul a Slave.</note> who, according to the Character of St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> water your Fields with the Tears of the <hi>Poor;</hi> you, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding your ſelves Lords and Sovereigns of all that God <note place="margin">Am. Ser. 59. de Au.</note> has lent you for your <hi>uſe,</hi> ſhut your Ears to the Cries of the Needy, and ſpend nothing but on <hi>Vice,</hi> or your ſelves; you, who conſume your whole Care in encreaſing your Heaps; and matter not how much you trample un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Foot the Law of God, and your injur'd Neighbour, ſo you can but advance upon them your Wealth and Poſſeſſions: Come hither, I ſay, and tell me, does your Soul <hi>command</hi> or <hi>ſerve?</hi> is ſhe <hi>Miſtreſs</hi> or <hi>Slave?</hi> But let the Royal Prophet anſwer for you; <hi>Dormierunt ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ſuum, &amp; nihil invenerunt omnes viri divitiarum in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 75.</note> 
               <hi>manibus ſuis. They ſlept their ſleep,</hi> ſays he, <hi>and all the men of Riches found nothing in their hands.</hi> Where tho'
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52010:9"/> the Words ſeem to import no more, than that Riches cannot exempt their <hi>Owners</hi> from dying, nor redeem them from Hell, if they are condemn'd to thoſe Flames; yet St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> has found a Criticiſm in them, a direct <note place="margin">L. de Nabuc. c. 15.</note> Anſwer to our Queſtion: for he takes notice, that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous Men are here call'd, <hi>Viri divitiarum, Men of Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es: Bene viros divitiarum appellat, non divitias virorum,</hi> there being a great difference between the <hi>Riches of Men</hi> and <hi>Men of Riches.</hi> We muſt ſee therefore, <hi>which</hi> belongs to <hi>which:</hi> Does the <hi>Maſter</hi> belong to his <hi>Servant,</hi> or the <hi>Servant</hi> to his <hi>Maſter?</hi> 'Tis out of doubt, the <hi>Servant</hi> is his <hi>Maſter</hi>'s. But by what are we to know, which is the <hi>Servant?</hi> This too is evident; for Servants are la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring and toyling in their ſeveral Employments, while the Maſter is taking his Eaſe, or divertiſing himſelf in ſome Recreation. Now let us look into the Houſe of a Covetous Man, and we ſhall be ſoon ſatisfied as to our <hi>Query:</hi> there we ſhall behold his Bags, his Treaſure, laid up, and oh! with how much Care and Sollicitude; all <hi>ſtill</hi> and <hi>quiet.</hi> But he, how <hi>buſie,</hi> how <hi>uneaſie!</hi> hard at work in ſecuring, and as earneſt in drawing in more. In this, his Memory is wholly taken up, 'tis the Concern of his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> and his Will and Affections are in a perpetual <hi>rack.</hi> And now, <hi>which</hi> here belongs to <hi>which?</hi> Which the Servant, which the Maſter? He's <hi>ſlaving</hi> it all day, while his Riches lye undiſturb'd, and without Employ. 'Tis certain therefore, the <hi>Riches</hi> are not of the <hi>Man,</hi> but he's the <hi>Man</hi> of his <hi>Riches. Viri divitiarum,</hi> ſays St. Ambroſe, <hi>ut oſtenderet eos, non poſſeſſores divitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Sup.</note> 
               <hi>eſſe, ſed à ſuis divitiis poſſideri, aliena cuſtodit ut fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulus, non tanquam Dominis ſuis utitur.</hi> And this is the Anſwer of the Pſalmiſt, calling Miſers, <hi>Men of Riches,</hi> to ſignifie to us, that while they <hi>wait</hi> on their Bags, like <hi>Servants,</hi> and do not <hi>uſe</hi> them, like <hi>Owners;</hi> they are not the <hi>Maſters of their</hi> Money, but its <hi>Slaves.</hi> And is
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52010:9"/> not this an intolerable Blindneſs of Men, that whenas God has given them Souls, that ſhould <hi>command</hi> and <hi>rule,</hi> they ſubject them to the <hi>Body,</hi> and make them Servants to droſs? O baſe Slavery of Covetouſneſs! and this is the Injury every Miſer does his Soul, thus does he debaſe it.</p>
            <p>But let us come now to the <hi>unclean</hi> and <hi>luxurious</hi> man. This is in all Propriety a <hi>Slave</hi> to his <hi>Fleſh.</hi> O poor Soul! did God create thee to ſerve the Body in theſe filthy and brutal Deſires? Is it not ſtrange, that a Soul ſo noble, which its <hi>Maker</hi> enrich'd with a <hi>Memory</hi> to reflect on his Benefits, with an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> to know his Greatneſs, and with a <hi>Will</hi> to love his Goodneſs, ſhould now employ all his Thoughts, his Deſires, his Memory, and Affections, in ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Body in its Uncleanneſs, and waiting on it, in thoſe its ſwiniſh Delights? O Baſeneſs, to be lamented with Tears of Blood! O Soul, unworthy of that Name! O, that thou would'ſt be aſham'd and confounded, to ſee thy ſelf a Slave to ſuch a beſtial Appetite! We read in <hi>Geneſis,</hi> that <hi>Potiphar</hi>'s Wife, full of Concupiſcence, caſt her Eyes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">c. 39.</note> 
               <hi>Joſeph,</hi> then a Servant in her Houſe: And 'tis very ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable, how the Septuagint (follow'd by St. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> and St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) word it. <hi>Injecit uxor domini oculos in Joſeph. And it came to paſs, that his Maſter's Wife cast her Eyes upon</hi> Joſeph. Now 'tis plain, that ſhe was not only his <hi>Master's Wife,</hi> but alſo <hi>Joſeph's Mistreſs,</hi> and <hi>Joſeph</hi> was her <hi>Servant.</hi> And it had been a more compendious Expreſſion, to have ſtil'd her his <hi>Mistreſs</hi> than his <hi>Maſter's Wife.</hi> 'Tis true, ſays St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> it had been more <hi>compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious,</hi> but not ſo <hi>proper:</hi> for why ſhould ſhe be call'd a <hi>Mistreſs</hi> who was ſuch a <hi>Slave</hi> to her Luſt? No, rather <hi>his Master's Wife, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xor Domini,</hi> is more agreeable; for ſhe is unworthy of the Name of <hi>Mistreſs,</hi> who is at the Command of ſo brutiſh a Paſſion: <hi>Rectè <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xor Domini,</hi> (they are the Words of St. <hi>Ambroſe) non ipſa Domina</hi> 
               <note place="margin">L. 1. de Joſ. c. 5.</note> 
               <hi>dicitur—Quomodo Domina, quae dominandi non habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat affectum, quae ſervilis libidinis incentiva praestabat?</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:52010:10"/> Scorn therefore, Chriſtian, to be led along by a <hi>Beaſt.</hi> Be aſham'd thus to debaſe thy <hi>Soul,</hi> and to make it a <hi>Servant</hi> to thy <hi>Body,</hi> which it ought to <hi>command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tell me, Chriſtian, what would'ſt thou ſay, if thou ſhould'ſt ſee, paſſing through the Streets, a Horſe nobly deck'd, his Saddle embroider'd with Gold, his Bridle of Silver, his Trappings wrought with Diamonds, and the Owner on his Back ſcarcely cover'd with Rags? Would'ſt not thou think that he had loſt his Judgment? And what if thou ſhould'ſt behold the Sight which the Wiſe-man ſaw; <hi>Vidi ſervos in equis, &amp; Principes ambulantes ſuper ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram quaſi ſervos. I have ſeen,</hi> ſays he, <hi>Servants upon Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccl. c. 10.</note> 
               <hi>and Princes walking on the Ground as Servants.</hi> Would not this have ſurpris'd thee? What! Peers and Princes at the Horſes Heels, waiting on their Servants! What a Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs! and yet no other Madneſs than thou art guilty of, when pamp'ring thy Body, and giving it all Reſpect and Attendance imaginable, thou neglect'ſt thy Soul, leaving it baſely disfigur'd, and cover'd over with the filth of Vice and Debauchery: no other Madneſs, Chriſtian, than thou art guilty of, as often as thou permitteſt thy Soul, that noble Lady, an Empreſs created for the Poſſeſſion of the Kingdom of Heaven, to be baſely dragg'd through all the Mazes of Sin, in Obedience to the <hi>ſlaviſh</hi> Commands of thy unruly Fleſh. O, how diſorderly and prepoſterous is this! And yet this every Sinner does as often as he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends againſt his Maker; and is it not a Madneſs, enough to fill your Hearts with Horror and Confuſion? But this is not all, ſays the Reverend Maſter <hi>Avila;</hi> a Sinner, when he offends, yet goes farther; he does not only make the <note place="margin">Av. in andi ſilia. c. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Slave</hi> ride in ſtate, and the <hi>Prince</hi> go on foot; but even makes the <hi>Beaſt</hi> lead the Prince bridled where it liſts. The <hi>Beaſt</hi> governs and commands, and the Prince likes well to be at ſuch a Beck. What Senſe would'ſt thou have, Chriſtian, of ſuch a monſtrous Spectacle? A noble Man, a Prince, one admirable both in <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>Arms,</hi> to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52010:10"/> be at the Command of a <hi>Bit,</hi> while a <hi>Brute</hi> has the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of the Bridle! What would'ſt thou ſay, Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, but that ſuch an one is only fit Company for Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men? Why then, ſay it to thy ſelf, <hi>Thou art he.</hi> For what is thy <hi>Body,</hi> but a kind of Animal, void of Reaſon and Underſtanding? and what is thy Soul, a Spirit, Prince of all Creatures, and capable of enjoying God? and thou permitteſt thy Body, with its beſtial Appetities, to lead thy Soul, without either Law or Reaſon, whereſoever they liſt. What is this, Sinner, what is this luxurious Man? Where is thy Underſtanding? and whither wilt thou go at laſt, drag'd by this wild and untam'd <hi>Beaſt?</hi> whither, but to thy eternal Ruine? And what can be the Concluſion of this diſorder'd Government, where the whole Command is in the hand of a Slave? Give ear a little.</p>
            <p>'Tis related in Hiſtory, that <hi>Semiramis</hi> from a <hi>Slave</hi> became <hi>Empreſs</hi> in <hi>Babylon;</hi> and it happen'd thus. <hi>Ninus,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Aelian. l. 3. de Var. hiſt.</note> then King, blind in Love, oblig'd himſelf to grant her whatſoever ſhe ſhould ask: ſhe deſir'd, that ſhe might have the Management of the Empire for one day; and immediately, by his Conſent, the Slave was rais'd to be a Sovereign. And being thus enthron'd, ſhe ordered ſeveral things, and was forthwith obey'd. Amongſt the reſt, ſhe commanded, that <hi>Ninus</hi> ſhould be ſeis'd, and have his Head cut off: this alſo was immediately done. For what elſe could be expected where Slavery rul'd the Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but Blood and Tyranny? And what is to be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Sinner, from this Dominion which thou haſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to thy Fleſh? What is to be the end of this Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience which thou yieldeſt to thy luſtful Appetites? What, but an eternal Death? O! how this was lamented by the Prophet <hi>Jeremy? Principes manu ſuſpenſi ſunt.</hi> He's <note place="margin">Lam. c. 5.</note> deploring the Miſeries which the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and he ſays, that the <hi>Chaldeans had hang'd up their Princes, and gave no Reſpect to the Ancients, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies ſenum non erubuerunt.</hi> All was full of Sadneſs and Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52010:11"/> And how came this, O <hi>Iſraelites?</hi> What was it that drew upon you theſe Afflictions? The Prophet had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd it juſt before: <hi>Aegypto dedimus manum, &amp; Aſſyrirs ut ſaturaremur pane.</hi> We, ſay the miſerable Captives, we deliver'd our ſelves to the <hi>Egyptians</hi> and the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> and we became Slaves to our Slaves. <hi>Servi dominati ſunt noſtri.</hi> And this was the Origin of all their Misfortunes. And you, O Chriſtian Souls, who are over-rul'd by your Slaves, by your carnal Appetites, what Concluſion can you expect? Death and eternal Torments wait for you. Oh, when will you reſolve to regain the Dominion over your Body? Will you put off, and neglect, till all Recovery is become impoſſible?</p>
            <p>Stay a while, and give ear to the Cries of thoſe miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Souls, who are in Hell Flames, there condemn'd to ſuffer for all Eternity; hear what they ſay; <hi>Ergo erravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus à via veritatis, &amp; juſtitiae lumen non luxit nobis. We</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Wiſ. 5.</note> 
               <hi>therefore have erred,</hi> is their common Voice. O poor Wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es! And now are you become ſenſible of it, when you are paſt Remedy? <hi>David</hi> was more circumſpect, who made this Reflection in time: <hi>Erravi ſicut ovis. I have err<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 118.</note> ſays <hi>David;</hi> and, <hi>We have erred,</hi> is the Cry of the <hi>Damned. David</hi> pronounc'd it in ſeaſon, it being in him the Voice of Repentance; but they have neglected their time, and in them 'tis only the effect of <hi>Deſpair. Ergo er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravimus; We have therefore erred,</hi> ſay they. A conſequence indeed, but very ill timed. The <hi>Antecedent</hi> in this Life, ſpent in Senſuality and Luſt, and the <hi>Conſequence</hi> in Hell? O! how this will <hi>conclude</hi> little before the Mercy-ſeat! Do you ſee, Chriſtians, how they lament? and how now, too late, they underſtand their <hi>Error?</hi> Reflect now a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and conſider what it was, and wherein their Error did conſiſt? But they declare it themſelves: <hi>Et juſtitiae lumen non luxit nobis.</hi> We follow'd not the Directions of Juſtice. <hi>Juſtice is that which gives to every one their own.</hi> And here they begin to underſtand what was their Error. That
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:52010:11"/> whereas they were bound to give to their Souls the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Reſpect of a Lady and Empreſs, and treat their Bodies like Servants; they, on the contrary, gave the Honour to the Body which did not belong to it, and abus'd their Souls, like Slaves. And this it is which they now fruitleſly lament, in the middle of their Torments: <hi>Juſtitiae lumen non luxit nobis;</hi> and the ſame will be their Complaint, without hopes of Remedy, for a long Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. <hi>Merito conqueruntur,</hi> ſays a Learned Author, <hi>in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferno</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Labat.</note> 
               <hi>damnati, ſe juſtitiae lumine caruiſſe, quia verè mali neſciunt unicuique rei debitam aeſtimationem tribuere; plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris enim corpus, quam animam faciunt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And, you Chriſtians, who hear this, till how long will you expect, before you underſtand your Error; till when there ſhall be no longer a Poſſibility of Remedy? <hi>Da illi honorem ſecundum meritum ſuum.</hi> Ah! rather let your Souls <hi>now</hi> have the Honour which is due to them; let them have the Precedency of your Body, in all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects. 'Tis baſe, and unbeſeeming a Chriſtian, to make his Body the whole Buſineſs of his Concern, while his Soul ſhall lye neglected, and be no part of his Care. Who is there of you ſo unreaſonable, that if he ſhould ſee his Houſe on Fire, his Servants in danger, his Wife expos'd to the Flames, would be firſt ſollicitous in ſaving his Servants? And yet, you Sinners, who have your Souls ready to be ſeiz'd on by Hell-fire, and your Fleſh burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Concupiſcence; to which do you run firſt with Aſſiſtance? Do you ſeek for Plenty of Tears to ſecure your Soul from the Flames of Hell; or the Water of vain Delights and unlawful Pleaſures, to extinguiſh, or rather ſatisfie the fire of your own Luſt? O Miſery, to thruſt your Souls more into the Flames, that your Bodies may be at eaſe! <hi>Da illi honorem.</hi> Ah Chriſtians, look rather to ſecure your <hi>Souls,</hi> tho' your <hi>Bodies</hi> periſh. The Body is attended by many Neceſſities, the Soul is in want of the Divine Grace: that the Body may be ſupplied, how
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:52010:12"/> little is it to run over the whole World, and to trample all Difficulties under foot; and ſhall no Pains be taken, that the Soul may have her Support? <hi>Da illi honorem.</hi> Is it the Soul of a Beaſt that you have within you, that it ſeems ſo unworthy of your Care? Who ever ſaw a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier receive the Dart in his Breaſt that he might preſerve his Shield untouch'd? The Serpent expoſes his Body to the Blow, to ſecure his Head, wherein his Soul reſides: and is it beſeeming a Chriſtian, to let his Soul lye open to all the Aſſaults of the Devil, that his Body may be kept harmleſs? No, the Body was intended to receive the Blows, and the Soul for Honour: <hi>Da illi honorem.</hi> And if thou can'ſt not comply ſo far, as to let thy Soul be the chief part of thy care, at leaſt, let it have an equal ſhare with thy Body. Take but notice, ſays St. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ho. 14. in Mat.</note> with how much Sollicitude thy Body is waited on, if in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpos'd; and how careful thou art, to free thy Eye from any thing that moleſts it: <hi>Animam autem tuam tantâ ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum congerie preſſam negligis. But thy Soul, lying under a Complication of Diſtempers, how little Concern for her De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery?</hi> Why is ſhe thus neglected? If thy Houſe be in danger of falling, thou do'ſt not let every Trifle divert thee from preventing the Ruine; but that which is moſt conſiderable, is certain of having thy firſt Aſſiſtance. Why, have the ſame care then for thy Soul, as for thy Houſe; at leaſt, as thou haſt for every Beaſt that goes along the High-way: <hi>Cadit aſinus,</hi> is the Complaint of St. <hi>Bernard, &amp; invenit, qui ſe ſublevet; cadit anima, &amp; non eſt qui</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ser. 14. in Cant.</note> 
               <hi>manum apponat. The Beast falls in the way,</hi> ſays the Saint, <hi>and there never want thoſe who will help it up: but the Soul falls into Sin, and ſhe's left in the mire.</hi> How unchriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an is this! Have the ſame care for it as thou haſt for the Garment thou weareſt; as for the Shoes under thy Feet, which thou haſt not Patience to ſee out of order. Let not thy Soul be in the Extremity of Wants, disfigur'd, nay, almoſt devour'd by Sin, and yet want Aſſiſtance: <hi>Da illi honorem ſecundum meritum ſuum.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:52010:12"/>
            <p>The Excellency of the Soul is yet made clearer to us from another Conſideration; in as much as it is <note place="margin">The Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Soul, in as much as 'tis the Image of God.</note> the <hi>Work</hi> of God, a work fram'd after his own <hi>Image.</hi> Upon which account, a much greater Reſpect is yet due to it. <hi>Da illi honorem.</hi> For the laying open this, make a ſhort Reflection, Chriſtians, how great an Eſteem Men generally have for any Picture or Statue, of the hand of any famous and excellent Artiſt. We have a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation in <hi>Pliny,</hi> that King <hi>Demetrius</hi> having laid Siege to <note place="margin">L. 35. c. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Rhodes,</hi> and there being no proſpect of his gaining the City, but by opening a Breach in that part of the Wall where ſtood a Picture, the Workmanſhip of the great <hi>Protogenes;</hi> he, not to injure the Piece, immediately com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Siege to be rais'd; chuſing rather to omit the making himſelf Maſter of ſo conſiderable a Poſt, than to prejudice the work of that great Maſter. <hi>Parcentemque Picturae fugit occaſio victoriae.</hi> And was not this Piece of <hi>Protogenes</hi> highly valued by <hi>Demetrius?</hi> And how much higher Value yet ought we to put upon our Souls for being the Work of God? it being certain, that whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever our Vicious Appetites are drawing forth in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Divine Law, and our wicked Deſires are making an Attack on the <hi>City</hi> of God, 'tis impoſſible we ſhould proceed in theſe Deſigns without defacing and even ruining our Souls, made by the hand of that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Artiſt. <hi>Manus tuae ſecerunt me. Thy hands have made</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 118.</note> 
               <hi>me.</hi> Let us have therefore a reſpect for our Souls, due to the Greatneſs of the Omnipotent hand that made us. But if we conſider a little farther, we ſhall diſcover our Souls to be not only the <hi>Work</hi> of God, but alſo his Image: a yet more forcing Argument for our Reſpect. There was in <hi>Athens</hi> a Statue of <hi>Minerva,</hi> made by <hi>Phidias,</hi> which was much celebrated among the Ancients: and the reaſon was, as <hi>Aristotle</hi> relates it, becauſe in the Shield of the Goddeſs, the Author had ſo ingeniouſly wrought his own Image, that 'twas impoſſible to efface this, without
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:52010:13"/> quite ruining the <hi>whole.</hi> How much more have we to ſay for our ſelves, Chriſtians, having Souls whoſe whole Subſtance is the very Image of their Creator? <hi>Ad imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem &amp; ſimilitudinem noſtram?</hi> How much greater is our Priviledge, bearing ſtamp'd in our Humane <hi>Being,</hi> the <note place="margin">Gen. 1.</note> Pourtraiture of our God: <hi>Signatum eſt ſuper nos lumen vultus tui Domine?</hi> But 'twill not be amiſs now, to hear from the Mouths of the Holy Fathers, in what manner our Soul is made after God's own Image.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>John Chryſostom</hi> ſays, it conſiſts in this; that as <hi>God</hi> is far above all Creatures whatſoever, ſo the <hi>Soul</hi> of Man <note place="margin">Chr. ho. 10. in. Gent.</note> is ſuperiour to all corporeal Beings, in Dignity, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and Power. St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſays, the <hi>Likeneſs</hi> conſiſts chiefly in that the Soul is endow'd with an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Aug. li. 8. in 1. Joan.</note> and that as God <hi>knows</hi> and <hi>loves</hi> himſelf, ſo alſo does the Soul. St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> becauſe as God is <hi>whole</hi> in the <hi>whole</hi> Univerſe, and <hi>whole</hi> in every part, ſo alſo is the <note place="margin">Am. l. dign. cor. hum.</note> Soul in reſpect of its Body: and as God is <hi>one</hi> in Eſſence, and <hi>three</hi> in Perſons; ſo is the Soul <hi>one</hi> in its <hi>Eſſence,</hi> and <hi>three</hi> in its <hi>Powers,</hi> the Will, Memory, and Underſtanding. S. <hi>John Damaſcen,</hi> that as God is <hi>free,</hi> ſo likewiſe the Soul. St. <hi>Thomas</hi> ſays, 'tis the Image of God, becauſe it <note place="margin">Dam. l. 2. Fid.</note> has a larger Portion of the Divine Perfections than any <note place="margin">O. Th. 1. p. q. 93. ar. 2.</note> other Creature. God has a <hi>Being,</hi> he has <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding:</hi> the Heavens and Elements partake of his <hi>Being;</hi> the Plants and Beaſts, of <hi>Life;</hi> and Angels of his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderstanding.</hi> But the Soul has a ſhare of all together, it is ennobled with a <hi>Being,</hi> with <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderstanding,</hi> all Excellencies of God himſelf. O Soul, did'ſt thou but know thy own Perfection, what eſteem would'ſt ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy ſelf! <hi>Agnoſce, O Christiane,</hi> ſays St. <hi>Leo, dignita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem tuam, &amp; divinae conſors factus naturae, noli in veterem</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ser. 1. de Nat. Do.</note> 
               <hi>vilitatem degeneri converſatione redire. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderstand,</hi> ſays he, <hi>and acknowledge thy own Excellency; and ſince God has rais'd thee to be Partaker of his own Being; be not ſo baſe, as by Sin to degrade thy ſelf from this ſo great an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:52010:13"/> For this only reaſon, Chriſtian, has God priviledg'd thy Soul, above all other Creatures; that thy Life may be anſwerable to thy Origin. <hi>Nobilem,</hi> ſays Eucherius, <hi>vult eſſe vitam tuam, qui tibi comiſit imaginem ſuam. He</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ho. 2. de ſymſ.</note> 
               <hi>that has imprinted his own Likeneſs in thy very Being, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends that thou ſhould'ſt be alſo like him in thy way of living.</hi> God's Life conſiſts in his knowing and loving himſelf; and it ought to be the Life of thy Soul, to know and love God. <hi>Dat unde ipſi quoque,</hi> are the Words of St. <hi>Leo, quod operatur, operemur.</hi> This is thy Being, this thy Obligation. But thou, Sinner, how haſt thou comply'd <note place="margin">Ser. 1. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 10. man.</note> with this thy Duty? O the Wickedneſs of Sin! How of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten haſt thou contemn'd and trodden upon this Dignity of thy Soul? How often haſt thou, by thy Villanies, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil'd, nay quite defac'd this Image of thy God? <hi>Denigra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta est facies, eorum ſuper carbones.</hi> Thou haſt made thy Soul more black than the very Coals; and at that time, when thou did'ſt commit thy Iniquities, thou didſt wipe off from thy Soul, that <hi>Likeneſs</hi> of the Bleſſed Trinity, which till then it wore, by the Grace of thy Maker. <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honorat animam,</hi> ſaid Rabbanus, <hi>qui peccatis illam polluit.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">L. 3. in Eccl. c. 3.</note> 
               <hi>He treats his Soul unworthily who pollutes it with Sin.</hi> But hear now, how it is that Sin ſtrikes off from the Soul the Image of God.</p>
            <p>The Soul of Man is, as it were, a <hi>Seal,</hi> bearing on it the <hi>Image</hi> of the Bleſſed <hi>Trinity: Tu ſignaculum ſimilitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 28.</note> And 'tis, as <hi>Rupertus</hi> deſcribes it, as if the King, with his Signet, ſhould imprint on Wax, his Arms and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture: <hi>Tanquam cera ſigilli Teſtatoris imagine ſignata.</hi> For <note place="margin">L. 2. in Gen. c. 2.</note> juſt ſo has God ſtamp'd on the <hi>Soul</hi> of Man, as in Wax, the <hi>likeneſs</hi> of his own Divine <hi>Being.</hi> But when a Sinner, unmindful of his Duty, offends againſt his Creator, O what a ſudden change, how this <hi>likeneſs</hi> ſoon diſappears! <hi>David,</hi> very ſenſible of this, exactly lays before us the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of it: <hi>Sicut fluit cera à facie ignis, ſic pereant peccatores</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 67.</note> 
               <hi>à facie Dei.</hi> Let any one take into his hand a piece of Wax,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52010:14"/> that has a Figure ſtamp'd on it, of a Lamb, a Dove, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> let him hold it to the Fire; the Wax ſoon diſſolves, and the Image it bore is utterly loſt: <hi>Sicut fluit cera à facie ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</hi> In like manner does Sin quite deſtroy the <hi>Likeneſs</hi> of God, imprinted on the Soul. <hi>Sic pereant peccatores à facie Dei.</hi> The Soul, when 'tis in Grace, is nobly beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with God's own <hi>Image;</hi> but approaching to the <hi>Fire</hi> of Concupiſcence, of Anger, of Pride, the Soul begins, in a manner to melt away, to be diſſolv'd; and the <hi>Image</hi> that it bore of its <hi>Maker</hi> is quite effac'd. <hi>A facie ignis,</hi> ſays <hi>Novarinus, à ſole ab aeſtu concupiſcentiae, ſic perit in eis</hi> 
               <note place="margin">In Elect.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; efluit imago dei, ut fluit cera à facie ignis.</hi> Conſider then, Sinner, what thou do'ſt, when thou putteſt thy ſelf in oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of offending God, when thou follow'ſt ill Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, giveſt ear to idle Diſcourſe; this is to hold the <hi>Wax</hi> out to the Fire; 'tis to wipe off the <hi>Likeneſs</hi> of God from thy Soul, and exchange it for that of the Devil. O, if thou did'ſt but behold, how foul and ugly thou art within, at the very Inſtant thou conſenteſt to any wicked Thought! if thou did'ſt but ſee how horrid and deform'd thy Soul is rendred by every mortal Sin! It may be call'd indeed the Image of its Creator, but ſo abus'd and disfigur'd, that there's no <hi>Likeneſs</hi> left. Stay therefore on this Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a little, and tell me for the preſent, what would'ſt thou ſay, if thou ſhould ſee, in the middle of the Street, ſome wicked <hi>Jew,</hi> or any other profane Miſcreant, tread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under his feet the Image of our Bleſſed Redeemer; and full of Contempt and Spite defacing it with a thouſand ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious Blows? What would'ſt thou ſay, Chriſtian, in this caſe? Would not thy Zeal put thee on to reſcue it from ſuch an unchriſtian Abuſe, and the Reſpect thou oweſt to him whom it repreſents, oblige thee to place it ſome where with Decency out of the reach of ſuch a helliſh Malice? Why look then, Sinner, ſee where thy Soul is; it lies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the feet of the Devils: Do'ſt thou know it? <hi>Cujus eſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 22.</note> 
               <hi>Imago haec? Whoſe is this Image?</hi> Is it not the Image of thy
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:52010:14"/> 
               <hi>God,</hi> and of thy <hi>Maker</hi> and <hi>Redeemer?</hi> See how 'tis abus'd, how disfigur'd; how 'tis without all Beauty and Grace. <hi>Egreſſus eſt à filia Sion omnis decor ejus.</hi> Why do'ſt not thou, without delay, redeem it from theſe Injuries? How can'ſt thou have Patience to ſee it trampled on by theſe infernal Furies? Ah! force it away, ſnatch it up, and by a ſincere and hearty Repentance, deliver it into the hands of thy God, that he may cleanſe it and reſtore it to its for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Beauty. <hi>Da illi honorem ſecundum meritum ſuum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as yet we have not ſeen the full worth of the <hi>Soul:</hi> it deſerves a yet higher eſteem from us, if we conſider at <note place="margin">The Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Soul redeem'd with the Blood of Jeſus. <hi>Ho. 2. de Symb.</hi>
               </note> how great a rate it was held by Jeſus Chriſt, and how much he gave for it. <hi>Quam pretioſus ſis,</hi> ſaid <hi>Eucherius, ſi Facto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem forte non credis, interroga Redemptorem. If thou know'ſt not, O Soul, to ſet a value upon thy ſelf, for being the Image of thy Creator, turn to thy Redeemer, and learn of him, how much thou art worth.</hi> O how much! <hi>St. Hilary,</hi> after a tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough Conſideration of this Point, ſays, that the Son of God gave ſo much for the Soul, <hi>that it ſeems in ſome man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ap. Euſ. hum. 8.</note> 
               <hi>to be worth even God himſelf: Tam copioſo munere ipſa Redemptio agitur, ut homo Deum valere videatur.</hi> St. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> ſaid it more expreſly, <hi>Sanguinem fudit <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicus Filius</hi> 
               <note place="margin">in Pſ. 102.</note> 
               <hi>Dei pro nobis. O Anima, erige te, tanti vales. The only Son of God ſhed his Blood for us: O Soul, look up, for ſo much art thou worth.</hi> Yes, Chriſtian Soul, have an eſteem for thy ſelf; the Son of God gave his Blood for thee. Thou art that <hi>Loſt Sheep</hi> for whoſe Recovery the Heavenly Paſtor undertook ſo laborious and chargeable a Journey. Thou art that precious <hi>Drachm</hi> that was <hi>loſt,</hi> for the regaining of which, that inacceſſible Light, the ſecond Perſon in the Bleſſed Trinity, was brought forth in our <hi>Humanity;</hi> God being made Man, for the Redemption of Man. Thou art that <hi>precious Jewel,</hi> for the purchaſing of which, the <hi>Divine Lapidary,</hi> who knew well its Value, gave all that he had: he gave his Blood, his Life, his Honour, he gave all, he gave his <hi>whole ſelf,</hi> that he might have thee; not thinking
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:52010:15"/> any price too high in ſuch a Purchaſe. See then, Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, how much thou ought'ſt to prize thy Soul, ſince Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt valued it at ſo high a rate, that he did not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lay down his Life for thee, but if 'twere neceſſary, would return, and do it a ſecond time. O bleſſed be ſuch Love, bleſſed be ſuch Goodneſs! But, thou, Sinner, tell me after all this, to whom does thy Soul belong, to whom haſt thou deliver'd it? Imagine with thy ſelf, that here comes in at preſent Jeſus Chriſt on one ſide, and the Devil on the other, both with a Deſign to buy this Jewel, thy Soul. Chriſt offers thee for it, all that thou haſt already heard. The Devil gives thee a little <hi>Smoak</hi> which he calls <hi>Honour;</hi> a little <hi>Droſs,</hi> which he calls <hi>Intereſt;</hi> a ſhort Imagination which he calls Guſt or Pleaſure. Now what haſt thou accepted? To which haſt thou given thy Soul? <hi>In iniquitatibus veſtris venditi eſtis.</hi> At the very Inſtant that thou conſented'ſt to ſin, you made a <hi>ſale</hi> of your Soul; but to whom? To Jeſus Chriſt, who gives ſo high for it, or to the Devil, who gives you nothing? O vile Contract of a Sinner! thou haſt ſold it to the Devil. St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> declares it to thee in plain terms; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nuſquiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cando</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ep. ad Rom. prop. 42.</note> 
               <hi>animam ſuam diabolo vendit, accepto tanquam precio, dulcedine temporalis voluptatis. Whoſoever ſins,</hi> ſays he, <hi>ſells his Soul to the Devil, at the price of ſome vain and fading Delight.</hi> But ſtay, Sinner, what do'ſt thou do? Do'ſt thou make a delivery of thy Soul to the Devil, being a Jewel which coſt the Son of God no leſs a price than his own Blood? Give ear a little to <hi>David,</hi> at that time when the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> had laid Siege to <hi>Bethlehem; O ſiquis mihi da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret potum aquae de ciſterna, quae eſt in Bethlehem. O</hi> (ſays <note place="margin">2 Kin. 23.</note> he) <hi>that ſome Man would give me drink of the Water of the Ciſtern that is in</hi> Bethlehem. Which when ſome of his Captains had heard, three of them broke through the Camp of the Enemies, and having drawn Water out of the Ciſtern of <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> they brought it to <hi>David.</hi> But he, <hi>noluit bihere, he would not drink; but offered it to our
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:52010:15"/> Lord. Libavit eam Domino.</hi> And he gives the reaſon; <hi>Num ſanguinem hominum iſtorum, &amp; animarum periculum bibam! Shall I drink</hi> (ſays he) <hi>the Blood of theſe Men, and the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril of their lives?</hi> Water that coſt ſo dear is not proper to be drunk, but to be made a Sacrifice: ſo that he ſeems to have reaſon'd thus with himſelf; This Water I may now either give to my ſelf, in ſatisfaction of my Appetite; or elſe to God, to whom it is due. But ſeeing, in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing, it coſt theſe Men the hazard of their Lives, I'll never let it be ſpent on a <hi>Guſt</hi> of my own, but I'll offer it up to my God: <hi>Libavit eam Domino.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ah Chriſtians, Chriſtians! If <hi>David</hi> put ſo high a Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue on a little Water, for reſpect of the Danger theſe men underwent; how ought you to eſteem your Souls, which have been purchas'd not only with Dangers, and an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interrupted toil of 33 Years, but even with the Life and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt? <hi>Quanti quaeſo,</hi> ſays a Learned Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, <hi>facienda eſt ſalus noſtra, non quidem hauſta periculo</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Labat.</note> 
               <hi>ſanguinis, &amp; vitae puri hominis, ſed ſanguine ipſo, &amp; vita ipſa hominis dei noſtri?</hi> Thou haſt coſt (O Soul) not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the danger of Life, but even Life it ſelf; and that not of Man, but of thy Redeemer, God and Man. And this Soul which has been ſo dearly purchas'd, thou baſely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livereſt into the hands of thy greateſt Enemy. And this, as the Prophet has it; <hi>Propter pugillum hordei, &amp; fragmen</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ez. 13.</note> 
               <hi>panis;</hi> for a handful of Barley and a morſel of Bread; for any of theſe little and inconſiderable <hi>Nothings</hi> of this World: and how many times even for leſs? how many times without Gain, without Guſt, without Honour? how many times haſt thou laid it down <hi>before hand;</hi> ſinning to day, on ſome deſign for the next Year? and how many times without all Hopes of any advantage, but rather with Diſcontents, Poverty, and publick Diſgrace? How often haſt thou gone forth, and like the Apoſtate-Diſciple, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited the Devils to take thy Soul at their own rate? <hi>Quid vultis mihi dare, &amp; ego eum vobis tradam?</hi> What delight
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:52010:16"/> will you give in Exchange of my Soul? O unreaſonable Vileneſs of Sinners! O monſtrous Ingratitude! What a Madneſs is this, exclaims St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> that a Chriſtian ſhould ſo diſeſteem his Soul, and make leſs Account of it than the Devil does? Satan offer'd to Chriſt, for <hi>his,</hi> all the Kingdoms in the World, when as yet he did not know him to be the Son of God; and the wicked Chriſtian de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers his without any Agreement, but ſtanding wholly to the Devil's Courteſie? <hi>Quis furor tam viles habere ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, quas etiam Daemon pretioſas habet!</hi> But tell me, Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <note place="margin">Ap. Hortig. coron. c. 9. §. 4.</note> what would'ſt thou take to be a <hi>Slave</hi> under the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane <hi>Turks,</hi> where thou art to expect nothing but a moſt cruel Uſage, Hunger, Blows, and Tyranny, without Eaſe, Reſt, or Sleep; or any ſatisfaction whatſoever? Is there any Price that can hire thee? I believe not. And yet of thy own Accord, thou makeſt thy ſelf one of the Devil's Slaves; thou putteſt thy ſelf under him, where thy Captivity ſhall be far more intollerable, and without all hopes of Redemption; ſince thou unworthily tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleſt under foot the Blood of thy Redeemer. <hi>Quare tibi tam vilis es, qui tam pretioſus es Deo? Why,</hi> ſays St. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logus, art thou ſo baſe to thy ſelf, who art ſo highly esteem'd by the God?</hi> Think of this with Shame and Confuſion; eſteem thy Soul as God eſteems it, at leaſt eſteem it more than the Devil himſelf does: <hi>Da illi honorem ſecundum meritum ſuum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Reſpect due to the Soul is rais'd yet one degree <note place="margin">The Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Soul, created for Glory.</note> higher, inaſmuch as the deſign of its firſt Creation was for the Enjoyment of an eternal Felicity, being made capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of God himſelf, and the Poſſeſſion of the clear and beatifical Viſion of its <hi>Maker</hi> in Glory. <hi>Secundum meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſuum, ſpe futurae mercedis,</hi> ſays <hi>Rabbanus,</hi> Give it its <note place="margin">L. 3. in Eccl. c. 3.</note> due, ſays he, on hope of a future Reward. God did not create thy Soul, Chriſtian, for the empty Vanities of this World: no, raiſe thy Thoughts higher. Hearken to Holy <hi>Job; Homo ad laborem naſcitur, &amp; avis ad volatum. Man
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:52010:16"/> is born to Labour, and the Bird to Flight;</hi> which, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Moral Gloſs,</hi> ſignifies, that the <hi>Body</hi> was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for Labour and Toil, but that the <hi>Soul</hi> was cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gl. mor. in</hi> Job. <hi>c. 5.</hi>
               </note> for to take its <hi>Flight</hi> to Heaven, and raiſe it ſelf to God. This Honour, this Title to the Kingdom of Heaven, was purchas'd for us by Jeſus Chriſt; who by his own moſt precious Blood did wipe out the <hi>Hand writing</hi> which the Devil held againſt us for our Excluſion from Glory: <hi>Delens quod adverſus nos erat chyrographum decreti.</hi> O Soul! and what an Honour is this, that thou wert not made <note place="margin">Coloſ. 2.</note> for Eating, Cloathing, and the little buſineſſes of the Earth! Thou haſt a <hi>Right</hi> to an eternal Crown; O, how would'ſt thou eſteem thy ſelf, if thou did'ſt but know what thou art!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ochozias,</hi> King of <hi>Juda,</hi> being dead, <hi>Athalia</hi> his Mother, full of Cruelty, and the Ambition of Ruling, immediately ſlew all the King's Sons, excepting only <hi>Joas,</hi> who was ſnatch'd from the Slaughter by <hi>Joſaba</hi> his Aunt, who, keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him in Diſguiſe ſix Years, brought him up in the Temple, till at length he was crowned King. <hi>Erat<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> cum</hi> 
               <note place="margin">4 Kin. 11.</note> 
               <hi>ea ſex annis clam in domo domini.</hi> Now thoſe that were not privy to the Secret, and knew him not to have a Right to the Kingdom, we may eaſily imagine, gave him no other Reſpects, than to other Youths, to whom his Education made him a Companion: while thoſe few that were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious of the whole Intrigue, honour'd him as a Prince, and ſerv'd him as their Sovereign; knowing that in a ſhort time he would come to be veſted with his Imperial Robes, and ſway the Scepter of <hi>Judah,</hi> tho' then he was but in a mean rank, and reputed as <hi>ordinary: Ab iis</hi> (ſays the <hi>Euſebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Euſ. Nier. ho. 8. ſect. 5.</note> of our Age) <hi>qui filium Regis noverant, magno habebatur ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nore, non quia regiis ornabatur inſignibus, ſed quia ornandus erat.</hi> O Chriſtian Souls! ſays the holy Evangeliſt St. <hi>John;</hi> now, while you are in this Life, your great Dignity is known but by few; you are as yet hid and in diſguiſe, and, like young <hi>Joas,</hi> without your princely Robes, without the Enſigns of Bliſs. <hi>Nondum apparuit, quid erimus;</hi> but there <note place="margin">1 Jo. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:52010:17"/> will come a time, when you ſhall be call'd to your King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and crown'd with Glory. <hi>Cum autem apparuerit ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ei erimus,</hi> &amp;c. O admirable Greatneſs! and is there any that knows how to reſpect you according to deſert! but have you, Chriſtian, made any Reflection upon this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of your Soul? I wiſh the groſs and foggy Delights of this tranſitory Life, have not rais'd a Miſt before your eyes, and quite clouded your Underſtanding. 'Tis very remarkable what <hi>Lyra</hi> relates of the famous <hi>Nebuchodono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zor,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lyr. in Dan. c. 1.</note> King of <hi>Babylon.</hi> He ſays, that he was no ſooner born, but expos'd in the Woods, where he was brought up at the care of a wild Goat; till at length a poor Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man paſſing by, took him, and brought him up amongſt his Children, without any diſtinction of Fare or Apparel. Now 'tis beyond all doubt, ſays a learned Modern, that <note place="margin">Cauſin.</note> if any one had come and aſſured him, that he was not the Son of his reputed Country-Father, but of a great Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch; that he was not born for the Harrow or Plow, but to have the Command over Empires; no doubt, but he would immediately have rais'd his Thoughts above thoſe ruſtick Concerns, and follow'd ſuch Deſigns as the nobleneſs of his Deſcent, and the hopes of a Crown, ſhould have ſuggeſted to him. Now give ear, Chriſtians, to what the Royal Prophet ſpeaks to you; <hi>Filii hominum</hi> (or as another Reading has it) <hi>Filii viri inclyti; ut quid diligitis vanitatem?</hi> Chriſtian Souls, Children of God, ſhut up with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this poor Cottage of Clay, and that have no other Knowledge than what is deriv'd to you by the Senſes; take notice, that you were created for an Empire. Let it not be always ſaid to you, that you are <hi>Duſt</hi> and <hi>Aſhes,</hi> this is only meant of the <hi>Body.</hi> But that you are of the Lineage of God; <hi>Ipſius &amp; genus ſumus.</hi> Let it be ſaid to <note place="margin">Act. 17.</note> you, that you were born for an unchangeable Crown; that theſe your mean Garments ſhall be chang'd into Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Robes, and your Sweats and Toil into Ornaments of an everlaſting Bliſs. Lift up your Eyes to Heaven: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:52010:17"/> the Sun, the Moon, the Stars; Why, you were created to be exalted above all theſe, to tread them under your feet. And if ſo; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t quid diligitis vanitatem?</hi> What, do you make <hi>this</hi> World your <hi>whole</hi> Concern, and buſie your ſelves in its ſhort-liv'd Vanities?</p>
            <p>If we ſhould behold a young Prince, chuſing Boys in the Street for his Companions, and inclin'd to no other Education than what was to be had from their uſeleſs and unmanly ſports; would it be prudent to mind him, that he was made of the ſame <hi>Earth</hi> with the reſt; or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with a reſpectful Check, to tell him, that thoſe common Toys were beneath his Quality, and that he ought to remember, he was born to a Crown? Souls of Chriſtians, you are <hi>Heirs to a Kingdom; Haeredes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> 
               <hi>quidem Dei:</hi> Lay aſide theſe vain concerns, ſo much inferiour to your <hi>Greatneſs: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t quid diligitis vanitatem?</hi> Why do you ſo diſeſteem and neglect that <hi>right</hi> to Glory which Jeſus Chriſt has purchas'd for you? The <hi>Title</hi> you have to any Temporal Eſtate, to any Lordſhip, or Principality, you maintain with all diligence and induſtry imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. And if any ſeek to injure you, or deprive you of it, you are not wont to ſit ſtill and behold your ſelf wrong'd with Patience and Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. God Almighty, by his Prophet, puts to you this Queſtion: <hi>Si</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Abd. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Fures introiſſent ad te, ſi latrones per noctem; quomodo conticuiſſes. If Thieves had gone into thee, if Robbers by night, how had'ſt thou held thy Peace?</hi> 'Tis certain you would have cry'd out for Aſſiſtance. Why then, ſince you ſee your ſelves ſpoil'd by Sin, of all your <hi>Titles</hi> and <hi>Right</hi> to Glory; why don't you cry out in an humble and hearty <hi>Confeſſion?</hi> Why don't you, in penitent ſighs, call upon him who alone is able to relieve you? And why, inſtead of this, do you diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble your ſelves from laying any claim to Heaven, and raſhly invite in thoſe whoſe buſineſs 'tis to rob your Souls of that <hi>Inheritance.</hi> Come, there's enough, enough of this Folly; have that Reſpect for your Souls which they deſerve, and maintain their Title to Bliſs: <hi>Da illi honorem ſecundùm meritum ſuum, ſpe futurae mercedis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, for the concluſion of this <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> 'twill contribute much to the imprinting this Doctrine in your Heart, if you reflect on the words of my Text, how that the Holy Ghoſt commanding you to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour your <hi>Soul,</hi> ſays, <hi>Da illi,</hi> in the ſingular; to mind us, that we have but <hi>one.</hi> 'Tis <hi>one,</hi> ſays the Spouſe in the <hi>Canticles, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na eſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumba</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 6. Pſ. 21.</note> 
               <hi>mea.</hi> 'Tis only <hi>one,</hi> ſays <hi>David; De manu Canis <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicam meam.</hi> Chriſtians, we have but <hi>one</hi> Soul, only <hi>one.</hi> God has given us (as diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>) two Eyes, two Ears, two Hands, and two Feet, <note place="margin">Orat. de an.</note> that if <hi>one</hi> be injur'd or loſt, we may have the comfort and aſſiſtance of the <hi>other: Animam vero dedit unam nobis; ſi hanc perdiderimus, quânam vivamus?</hi> But he has given us but <hi>one</hi> Soul; and if this be loſt have we any other for a Supply? No, certainly. Why then ſhould
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:52010:18"/> we be ſo inconſiderate, as to hazard <hi>this</hi> every moment, and to put it to the venture of a remedileſs Eternity of Miſeries? In Noblemens Houſes 'tis cuſtomary at night, to have two or three Lights in their Preſence, that ſo if by any Accident one ſhould fail, they may not remain in Darkneſs, but be ſupply'd by the other. But, Chriſtians have but <hi>one Light, one Soul</hi> within them, and if this miſcarry, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is to be expected, but an eternal Darkneſs, ſubject to the juſt Indignation of their God. You have read, how full of Wrath <hi>David</hi> was when the Parable of the <hi>little Ewe</hi> was put to him by <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet. He demanded Juſtice at the King's hands, for that a Rich man in the City, who abounded in Sheep and Oxen, took away from a certain Poor man a <hi>little Ewe,</hi> whoſe Stock went not beyond this <hi>one,</hi> and of this made a Feaſt for the entertainment of a Stranger that came to his Houſe; <hi>Nihil habebat omnino praeter ovem unam parvulam.</hi> At which <hi>David,</hi> being fill'd with Indignation, proteſted before the Lord, <hi>Vivit Dominus,</hi> that the Man that had done the thing ſhould pay it fourfold. At which the Prophet replying to the King, ſaid, <hi>Thou art the Man,</hi> againſt whom thou art ſo juſtly angry. And I may turn to thee, Sinner, and ſay, <hi>Thou art the Man.</hi> For is not thy <hi>Soul,</hi> that little Sheep, which Chriſt bought at the price of his own Blood; is it not that which God created, redeem'd, and has deſign'd for his Eternal Glory? And this thou offereſt to the Devil thy <hi>Gueſt;</hi> thou makeſt of it a Banquet, to entertain <hi>Lucifer,</hi> being only <hi>one,</hi> and which has coſt thy God ſo dear. And doſt not thou in this provoke the omnipotent hand of God againſt thee? Thou haſt one only <hi>Jewel,</hi> and this thou mortgageſt every day more and more, by thy Offences: it will come one day to remain wholly in the power of thy Enemy, to whom thou haſt thus engag'd it. Thou haſt only one piece of Land, and this thou neglecteſt to Till or Plant with good Works; wilt not thou by this means come to periſh eternally with Hunger? Thou haſt one only Houſe, and ſeeing this all in flames, conſuming with the Fire of Sin, thou doſt not at all bring Relief, nor ſeek plenty of <hi>Tears</hi> to extinguiſh it: and is not this the way to caſt thy Soul into Hell, as a Fewel for thoſe never-ending Flames? Ah, rather ſeek to prevent theſe Miſchleſs, and give the Honour to the Soul which is due to it. <hi>Da illi honorem ſecundum meritum ſuum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Come therefore, Chriſtian; <hi>Miſerere Animae tuae,</hi> take Compaſſion on thy poor Soul. Enter a while, retire within thy ſelf, ſays St. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin,</hi> and thou wilt find thy <hi>Soul,</hi> neceſſitous and miſerable, asking thee an Alms, begging for Relief. <hi>Redi ad conſcientiam tuam, &amp; ibi</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ser. 31. de verb. Dom.</hi> Iſa. 46.</note> 
               <hi>invenies, egentem, &amp; mendicantem animam tuam.</hi> Look in, and thou wilt behold the <hi>Miſtreſs</hi> ſerving, and the <hi>Slave</hi> commanding. Look in, and thou wilt ſee the <hi>Image</hi> of God, under the feet of the Devil. Look
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:52010:18"/> in, and thou wilt ſee that which Jeſus Chriſt bought at the Price of his own Blood, ſold and made over to Satan for a little Air for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. Look in, Sinner, and thou wilt find that which was created for an everlaſting Kingdom, to be now obnoxious to an eternal Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominy. Look in, and thou wilt behold thy poor Soul, without God, without Life: <hi>Semiviva relicta,</hi> waiting every Inſtant to be thrown into Hell. <hi>Miſerere animae tuae, Take pity on thy Soul.</hi> Behold her made a publick Manſion of Devils, where they enter and dwell without any oppoſition, by wicked Thoughts, profane Words, and worſe Works. <hi>Fac ergo eleemoſynam animae tuae.</hi> Bring therefore ſome <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi ſup.</note> Relief, ſaith St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> to thy Soul, in this her extremity of wants; give ear to her Petitions, and be not deaf to her ſad Complaints in theſe her Miſeries. And for the preſent be attentive to this Relation:</p>
            <p>We read of a certain wretched Man, who living unmindful of <note place="margin">Tho. de Cantipr. l. 2. apum. c. 56.</note> God and his Soul, gave himſelf up wholly to Licentiouſneſs and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchery. On an occaſion, he was making merry with his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, eating and drinking without meaſure; and amongſt other things, they began a Diſcourſe of, <hi>What was to be after this Life?</hi> Many things had been ſaid, when behold a Stranger comes in, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to know the matter of their Diſpute: to whom this miſerable man; Here, ſays he, we are entertain'd with a pretty Debate, of what is to become of our Souls when they have left the Body; but for my part, if I could find a Chapman, I would ſell my Soul, and feaſt my Friends with the price of it. At which, the Stranger anſwer'd, that he would buy it: and forthwith the Bargain being agreed on, paid the Money; with which the other entertain'd the whole Company. But night being come, he that had made the Purchaſe ſaid, 'Tis now time we ſhould break up, and therefore, I declare to you all, that I am the Devil: this Wretch hath made a delivery to me of his Soul, and I have Command of the Higheſt, to carry him away, both Soul and Body; and immediately taking him into the Air, he diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd, and hurried him into the bottomleſs Pit of Hell, where he is now conſuming in thoſe never-ending Flames, and ſhall be, as long as God ſhall be God, without hopes of Eaſe or Relief.</p>
            <p>See now, Sinner, what is the Concluſion of thoſe who neglect their Soul; the ſame miſerable Fate attends thee, if thou doſt not amend: thou haſt yet time to prevent all, by a ſerious and hearty Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: at that time when thou didſt ſin againſt thy God, thou mad'ſt over thy Soul to the Devil; but the Contract may be yet broken off, and made null, by a true Sorrow and an hearty Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Come then, make haſte to revoke thy Word, and undoe ſo unjuſt a Bargain. Alledge that there was fraud in the Sale, that the Purchaſer has abus'd the Jewel, and cheated the Owner. Let the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:52010:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> abundance of thy Tears cancel the Writings, and the Intenſeneſs of thy Repentance make void all the Obligations, by which thou delivered'ſt thy ſelf to the Power of <hi>Satan.</hi> Chriſtian, there's enough of Blindneſs. You have only <hi>one</hi> God, you have <hi>one</hi> Soul alone, and but <hi>once</hi> can you expect to dye; Why is it that you continue in Sin? Your Soul in Poſſeſſion of the Devil! Your Soul in danger to be damn'd eternally! Oh, why don't you proſtrate your ſelves at the feet of your merciful Redeemer, of your Crucified Jeſus? See what he gave for your Soul; he ſpilt his Blood <hi>once</hi> for you, and would do it again a thouſand times for your Salvation; and will you ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue Slaves to Sin and the Devil? Sons of my Blood (he ſays to you) Children of my Love, for your Soul's Good was I nail'd to the Croſs, and my <hi>Wounds,</hi> yet freſh, are crying aloud to you, to forſake your evil ways, and to follow me. And what Anſwer do you return, Chriſtians, to theſe Complaints of your Loving Redeemer? Do you ſay, you <hi>will not?</hi> O never, never let it be ſo; but rather with a true ſenſe of your Sins, and a hearty ſorrow for having liv'd ſo long in Blindneſs, fall down at his Feet, and ſay from the bottom of your Heart; My Lord Jeſus Chriſt, my God, my Father, my Redeemer, in whom I believe, in whom I put my Truſt, and whom I love more than my own Life, more than my Soul, and above all things whatſoever: it repents me, Dear Lord, it repents me from my heart, that I have offended againſt thee. O infinite Goodneſs! O my Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus! O, that I had never broken thy Commandments! O, that I had died a thouſand Deaths, rather than have ſinn'd againſt thy Divine Majeſty! I am ſorry for thy ſake alone, for being who thou art, ſo infinitely holy, ſo good, ſo amiable; I am ſorry, Dear Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that I have injur'd thee with my Offences. And here I make a firm purpoſe, by the aſſiſtance of thy Grace, never more to ſin: I offer here a thouſand Lives, rather than return to my Iniquity; and reſolve to avoid all Occaſions and Dangers of committing any Crime againſt thee: I here intend to make a ſincere Confeſſion of all my Wickedneſs, and to comply with all the Obligations that ſhall be laid on me; and I truſt, that through the Merits and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of my loving Redeemer, I ſhall obtain pardon of all my Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. I have ſinned, Lord I have ſinned; but thou, my God, have Mercy on me; Mercy, Bleſſed Saviour; Mercy, my Jeſus. I love thee above all things, O my Jeſus: Let thy Love, let thy Faith live and encreaſe; and repleniſh us with thy Grace, the Pledge of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Glory, <hi>ad quam nos perducat Sancta &amp; individua Trinitas, Pater, &amp; Filius, &amp; Spiritus Sanctus,</hi> to which, God of his infinite Mercy bring us. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
